The wound must be infected. I need to see it.
‫لا بد أن الجرح ملوث، يجب أن أراه.
I…
‫أنا…
I will do it myself.
‫سأفعل ذلك بنفسي.
Your Royal Highness.
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
This is…
‫هذا…
my secret.
‫سرّي.
What do you mean His Royal Highness has disappeared?
‫ماذا تعني بأن صاحب السموّ الملكي قد اختفى؟
While the procession was crossing the woods,
‫بينما كان الموكب يعبر الغابة،
Commander Yoon and his men took His Royal Highness
‫خطف القائد "يون" ورجاله صاحب السموّ الملكي
while disguised as bandits.
‫وهم متنكرون كقطّاع طرق.
Commander Yoon?
‫القائد "يون"؟
So His Royal Highness still has not been found?
‫إذًا لم يتم العثور على سموّه بعد؟
Commander Yoon is now in Inspector Jung's custody,
‫القائد "يون" مُحتجز ‫من قبل المفتش "جونغ" الآن،
so we will soon find him.
‫لذا سنجده قريبًا.
His Majesty must have ordered to keep His Royal Highness alive.
‫لا بد أن جلالة الملك ‫قد أمر بإبقاء سموّه على قيد الحياة.
Even after ordering His Royal Highness' dethronement,
‫حتى بعد إصدار الأمر بخلع صاحب السموّ،
he used you to take him to safety.
‫استغلّك ليأخذه إلى مكان آمن.
I was surprised though.
‫لكنني تفاجأت.
Disguising him as a woman was a neat trick.
‫جعله يتنكر كامرأة كان حيلة متقنة.
Dam-i, was it?
‫اسمها "دامي"، أليس كذلك؟
I saw her in him.
‫رأيتها فيه.
Well…
‫حسنًا…
I guess that is obvious since they were twins.
‫أظن أن ذلك واضح بما أنهما توأمان.
Why go to such lengths…
‫لماذا تتكبد كل هذا العناء…
to track him down?
‫لتتعقبه؟
As you said,
‫كما قلت،
he is already a dethroned prince.
‫هو أمير مخلوع أصلًا.
It's about time…
‫حان الوقت…
you let him go.
‫لتدعه وشأنه.
That is not my decision to make.
‫هذا ليس قراري.
It is Lord Sangheon's.
‫إنه قرار اللورد "سانغهيون".
A suspicious man and woman were seen in the woods near Mount Hwanghak.
‫شُوهد رجل وامرأة مثيران للريبة ‫في الغابة قرب جبل "هوانغهاك".
Stand guard here until I come back.
‫احرس هذا المكان حتى أعود.
I should treat your wound first.
‫يجب أن أعالج جرحك أولًا.
I will go and gather some firewood.
‫سأذهب لأجمع بعض الحطب للنار.
EPISODE 13
‫"الحلقة الـ13"
Over here! I found blood.
‫هنا! وجدت دمًا.
He could not have gone too far.
‫لا يمكن أن يكون قد ابتعد كثيرًا.
Search this area thoroughly.
‫فتّشوا هذه المنطقة جيدًا.
His Royal Highness must be found. Do you understand?
‫يجب أن نعثر على صاحب السموّ، هل تفهمون؟
-Yes, Inspector.
‫- نعم أيها المفتش.
Carry on!
‫تابعوا التقدم!
Is Lord Jaeun's location still unknown?
‫هل ما زال مكان اللورد "جايون" مجهولًا؟
We are still searching.
‫ما زلنا نبحث.
Why are you not resting?
‫لماذا لم تستريحي؟
Is there…
‫هل…
something you need?
‫تحتاجين إلى شيء؟
I did not want to be alone.
‫لم أُرد أن أكون بمفردي.
Why are you not asking me anything?
‫لماذا لا تسألني عن شيء؟
About me, I mean.
‫أقصد بشأني.
I know this came as a shock to you.
‫أعلم أن هذا سبّب لك صدمة.
You probably resent me…
‫ربما أنت مستاء مني…
for deceiving you.
‫لأنني خدعتك.
Yes.
‫نعم.
I do feel resentment.
‫أشعر بالاستياء فعلًا.
Not toward you,
‫ليس منك،
but toward myself.
‫لكن من نفسي.
You had to manage
‫كان عليك أن تواجهي
the hardships all by yourself.
‫المصاعب بمفردك.
I apologize…
‫أعتذر…
for not realizing sooner.
‫لعدم إدراك الأمر في وقت أبكر.
We were born twins.
‫وُلدنا توأمين.
Me and my brother, the eldest son of the Crown Prince.
‫أنا وأخي، الابن الأكبر لوليّ العهد.
After he died…
‫بعد موته…
I had to take his place.
‫كان عليّ أخذ مكانه.
While deceiving people,
‫بينما كنت أخدع الناس،
I lived a life that was not mine.
‫عشت حياة لم تكن لي.
You may put off…
‫يمكنك تأجيل…
telling me about the hardships.
‫إخباري عن الصعوبات.
Right now, your health matters more.
‫الآن، صحتك مهمة أكثر.
So please do not force yourself to tell me your story.
‫لذا أرجوك لا تضغطي على نفسك لإخباري بقصتك.
Not now.
‫ليس الآن.
No! No, Father. Please.
‫لا! لا يا أبي، أرجوك.
I may not be able
‫ربما لا أتمكن
to tell you everything later on.
‫من إخبارك بكل شيء لاحقًا.
I will not hold that against you.
‫لن ألومك على ذلك.
Because…
‫لأنه…
nothing has changed for me.
‫لم يتغير شيء بالنسبة لي.
It is you that I am looking at.
‫أنت من أنظر إليها.
And that is all I need.
‫وهذا كل ما أحتاج إليه.
As long as I am with you…
‫طالما أنا معك…
I do not need anything else.
‫لا أحتاج إلى أي شيء آخر.
You may hand that over. I will take it to him.
‫يمكنك أن تعطيني هذا، سأوصله إليه.
Oh, of course.
‫بالطبع.
Why did you help me?
‫لماذا ساعدتني؟
It takes determination to take a life,
‫سلب حياة شخص يتطلب إصرارًا،
but I do not see that in you today.
‫لكنني لا أرى هذا فيك اليوم.
Answer me.
‫أجبني.
Why did you have Commander Yoon tail me
‫لماذا جعلت القائد "يون" يراقبني
and save me from trouble?
‫وينقذني من المأزق؟
What is your reason for killing them?
‫ما هو دافعك لقتلهم؟
Did you think murdering them would solve everything?
‫هل ظننت أن قتلهم سيحلّ كل شيء؟
Or was it just your way of shedding pent-up anger?
‫أم أنها كانت طريقتك ‫في التخلص من الغضب المكبوت؟
It is why traitor Kang Hwa-gil will hereby be executed by beheading.
‫"ولهذا السبب ‫سيُعدم الخائن (هوا غيل كانغ) بقطع رأسه."
Goodness.
‫يا للهول.
As if you know anything.
‫وكأنك تعرف أي شيء.
You know…
‫أنت لا تعرف…
nothing about me.
‫أي شيء عني.
"The last night of the year."
‫"الليلة الأخيرة من العام."
It implies, "To discard what's old before welcoming a new year."
‫إنها توحي بـ"التخلص من القديم ‫قبل الترحيب بالعام الجديد."
Your father and I…
‫أنا ووالدك…
each shared a piece of that tally as a token of our promise
‫أخذ كل منا تلك البطاقة كرمز لوعدنا
to build a new world.
‫ببناء عالم جديد.
I…
‫أنا…
failed to keep that promise,
‫فشلت في الحفاظ على ذلك الوعد،
lost a good friend in the process, and became a helpless king…
‫وفقدت صديقًا طيبًا أثناء ذلك، ‫وأصبحت ملكًا عاجزًا…
who abandoned his own child.
‫تخلى عن ابنه.
But…
‫لكن…
there never was a day when I forgot about our promise.
‫لم أنس وعدنا يومًا.
And I will remember it until the day I die.
‫وسأتذكره حتى يوم مماتي.
The world your father and I dreamed of.
‫العالم الذي حلمنا به أنا ووالدك.
I will build that world.
‫سأبني ذلك العالم.
Your Majesty, your herbal tonic will be served.
‫جلالتك، سأقدّم لك المنشط العشبي الخاص بك.
I thought I heard you conversing
‫ظننت أنني سمعتك تتحدث
and assumed someone was here.
‫وافترضت أن أحدًا ما هنا.
I was reading my book out loud.
‫كنت أقرأ كتابي بصوت عال.
I see.
‫فهمت.
Eun-seo.
‫"إيون سيو".
Your father's grave is by the wide rock
‫قبر والدك عند الصخرة الكبيرة
halfway up Mount Gwanak.
‫في منتصف الطريق إلى جبل "غواناك".
You should visit him.
‫يجب أن تزوره.
Your Majesty!
‫جلالتك!
-Your Majesty!
‫- جلالتك!
-Your Majesty.
‫- جلالتك.
Your Majesty!
‫جلالتك!
-Your Majesty! -Your Majesty…
‫- جلالتك! ‫- جلالتك…
Your Majesty!
‫جلالتك!
-Your Majesty!
‫- جلالتك!
Please come back, Your Majesty!
‫عُد رجاءً يا صاحب الجلالة!
Just a moment.
‫لحظة واحدة.
Can we stay like this for just a moment?
‫هل يمكننا البقاء هكذا للحظة فقط؟
Are you feeling better?
‫هل تشعرين بتحسن؟
It…
‫إنه…
still hurts a lot.
‫ما زال يؤلمني كثيرًا.
You will be all right…
‫ستكونين بخير…
since I will be by your side.
‫لأنني سأكون إلى جانبك.
Being with me…
‫الوجود معي…
will make you a fugitive for life.
‫سيجعلك هاربًا مدى الحياة.
You will have to sever ties with family and friends
‫سيكون عليك قطع علاقتك بالعائلة والأصدقاء
and live in the shadows.
‫وستعيش متخفيًا.
I would not mind that.
‫لن أمانع ذلك.
After all,
‫في النهاية،
it is the life I have always dreamed of.
‫إنها الحياة التي لطالما حلمت بها.
Once we leave this place and arrive somewhere safe,
‫حالما نغادر هذا المكان ونصل إلى مكان آمن،
I will find us a small house first.
‫سأجد لنا منزلًا صغيرًا أولًا.
By the shore would be most preferable…
‫من الأفضل أن يكون قرب الشاطئ…
and I will need a fishing boat.
‫وسأحتاج إلى قارب صيد.
I will come home around sundown and cook you dinner
‫سأعود إلى المنزل ‫عند غروب الشمس وأطهو لك العشاء
with the fish that I catch.
‫بالأسماك التي أصطادها.
Also…
‫وأيضًا…
we will go on an outing on market day.
‫سنخرج في نزهة في يوم السوق.
There…
‫هناك…
I will buy you a small gift
‫سأشتري لك هدية صغيرة
without you knowing.
‫من دون علمك.
Is there something you would like?
‫هل ثمّة ما ترغبين فيه؟
I will take my time
‫سآخذ وقتي
and think of what I would like to receive from you.
‫للتفكير فيما أريد أن أتلقاه منك.
You there. Could you give me some water?
‫يا هذا، هل يمكنك أن تعطيني بعض الماء؟
Here you go.
‫تفضل.
Lord Jaeun!
‫اللورد "جايون"!
Are you all right?
‫هل أنت بخير؟
I followed the soldiers guarding this place.
‫تبعت الجنود الذين يحرسون هذا المكان.
What happened? Where is His Royal Highness?
‫ماذا حدث؟ أين صاحب السموّ الملكي؟
We parted ways at the dock.
‫افترقنا عند الرصيف البحري.
He most likely headed to Mount Hwanghak.
‫على الأرجح أنه توجه إلى جبل "هوانغهاك".
Jung Seok-jo went after him with his men
‫لاحقه "سيوك جو جونغ" مع رجاله،
which is why we must find him first.
‫لهذا السبب يجب أن نجده أولًا.
-We should go. -Yes.
‫- يجب أن نذهب. ‫- نعم.
I found a bloodstain here!
‫وجدت بقعة دم هنا!
Over there!
‫هناك!
I told you to wait for me in the woods.
‫طلبت منك انتظاري في الغابة.
You must be exhausted.
‫لا بد أنك مرهقة.
Court Lady Kim and Eunuch Hong will be worried about me.
‫ستقلق سيدة البلاط "كيم" ‫والمخصيّ "هونغ" بشأني.
Time is of the essence,
‫الوقت مهم جدًا،
so it would be wiser to get moving.
‫لذا سيكون من الحكمة أن نتحرك.
Are you sure it is not because you do not wish to be away from me?
‫هل أنت واثقة أن السبب ‫لا يتعلق برغبتك في عدم الابتعاد عني؟
Pardon?
‫عفوًا؟
You said the safe house was on the other side of Mount Bukseong.
‫قلت إن المنزل الآمن ‫في الجهة الأخرى من جبل "بوكسيونغ".
Yes.
‫نعم.
It is where we will reunite with everyone else.
‫إنه المكان الذي سنجتمع فيه مع الجميع.
Then you should change into something less conspicuous first.
‫إذًا، يجب عليك أولًا ‫أن ترتدي ملابس لا تلفت الانتباه كثيرًا.
Here you go.
‫تفضل.
Thank you.
‫شكرًا لك.
It is my pleasure.
‫هذا من دواعي سروري.
Shall we?
‫هلّا نذهب؟
I found a place where you can change.
‫وجدت مكانًا يمكنك أن تبدلي ملابسك فيه.
Right. Of course.
‫صحيح، بالطبع.
I think it will be best if we split up.
‫أظن أنه من الأفضل أن نفترق.
His Royal Highness could have gone to the safe house,
‫ربما ذهب صاحب السموّ الملكي ‫إلى المنزل الآمن،
so why don't you check there?
‫فلم لا تذهب وتبحث هناك؟
I will search here a little more.
‫سأبحث هنا قليلًا بعد.
All right.
‫حسنًا.
What is this?
‫ما هذا؟
I thought you might be hungry.
‫ظننت أنك قد تكونين جائعة.
Try it. It will satisfy your palate.
‫تذوّقيه، سيرضي ذوقك.
Do the clothes fit well?
‫هل الملابس مناسبة؟
Yes.
‫نعم.
I finally feel like I am in the right clothes.
‫أشعر أخيرًا أنني أرتدي الملابس المناسبة.
Please do not be too wistful.
‫أرجوك لا تكوني حزينة جدًا.
Once we leave this place, I will buy you pretty clothes every day.
‫حالما نغادر هذا المكان، ‫سأشتري لك ملابس جميلة كل يوم.
Wear dresses or tie a ribbon in your hair all you want.
‫ارتدي الفساتين أو اربطي شريطًا ‫في شعرك كما تشائين.
No one will care.
‫لن يهتم أحد.
Actually…
‫في الواقع…
it still does not seem real to me.
‫ما زال الأمر لا يبدو حقيقيًا بالنسبة لي.
That I am leaving the palace to finally live my own life.
‫مغادرتي القصر لأعيش حياتي الخاصة أخيرًا.
Your Royal Highness, could you wait here for just a moment?
‫يا صاحبة السموّ الملكي، ‫هل يمكنك الانتظار هنا للحظة؟
I forgot to buy something.
‫نسيت أن أشتري شيئًا.
-Buy what? -Please enjoy that as you wait!
‫- ماذا ستشتري؟ ‫- استمتعي بذلك أثناء الانتظار رجاءً!
It will not take long.
‫لن يستغرق الأمر طويلًا.
Drop your sword if you wish to save their lives.
‫اخفض سيفك إن كنت تريد أن تنقذ حياتهما.
How dare you.
‫كيف تجرؤ؟
-How dare you! -Forgive me,
‫- كيف تجرؤ! ‫- سامحني،
but it is time you returned to the palace.
‫لكن حان الوقت لتعود إلى القصر.
What do you mean, the palace?
‫ماذا تعني بالقصر؟
Grandfather, what brings you here?
‫جدّي، ما الذي أتى بك إلى هنا؟
His Majesty…
‫صاحب الجلالة…
has passed away.
‫قد مات.
Your Royal Highness, you must immediately return to the palace.
‫يجب أن تعود إلى القصر حالًا ‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
What are you saying?
‫ماذا تقول؟
What do you mean Father has passed away?
‫ماذا تعني بأن أبي مات؟
Is it true that the King passed away?
‫هل صحيح أن الملك تُوفي؟
Yes. Did you not see the soldiers moving out?
‫نعم، ألم تر الجنود يخرجون؟
What good is there in being a king if you die like the rest of us?
‫ما فائدة أن يكون ملكًا إن كان يموت مثلنا؟
Talk about life being futile.
‫الحياة عديمة الجدوى.
He was poisoned?
‫تمّ تسميمه؟
According to the physician who last saw him,
‫وفقًا للطبيب الذي رآه آخر مرة،
his body showed discoloration which indicates poisoning.
‫أظهر جسده تغيرًا في اللون ‫وهذا يشير إلى التسمم.
Who could have done such a thing?
‫من يمكنه أن يفعل شيئًا كهذا؟
This is nothing to ponder over, Your Highness.
‫هذا أمر لا يستدعي التفكير سموّك.
Please appoint a successor to the throne and do not let this drag on.
‫أرجو أن تعيّني وريثًا للعرش ‫ولا تدعي الأمر يطول.
This is a state funeral.
‫إنها جنازة رسمية.
How dare you speak of it in the presence of his coffin.
‫كيف تجرؤ على التحدث ‫عن الأمر في حضرة تابوته.
His Majesty's untimely death
‫وفاة جلالته المفاجئة
on top of the Crown Prince's dethronement is bringing forth social unrest.
‫بالإضافة إلى خلع وليّ العهد عن العرش ‫تسبّبا بالاضطرابات الاجتماعية.
You must decide who succeeds the throne before there is an uproar, Your Highness.
‫يجب أن تقرري من سيخلفه على العرش ‫قبل أن يحدث اضطراب يا صاحبة السموّ.
-Please make a decision, Your Highness.
‫- رجاءً اتخذي قرارًا سموّك.
Why is it that Lord Sangheon is not present?
‫لماذا اللورد "سانغهيون" ليس موجودًا؟
-Your Royal Highness.
‫- صاحب السموّ الملكي.
How is the Crown Prince here?
‫كيف يكون وليّ العهد موجودًا هنا؟
I was late because I had to escort the Crown Prince, Your Highness.
‫تأخرت لأنه كان عليّ ‫أن أرافق وليّ العهد سموّك.
Father…
‫أبي…
Father.
‫أبي.
MEMORIAL TABLET OF KING HYEJONG
‫"لوح تذكاري للملك (هيجونغ)"
A dethroned Crown Prince
‫وليّ العهد المخلوع
who broke away from his road to exile is back at the palace.
‫الذي هرب ‫أثناء رحلته إلى المنفى عاد إلى القصر.
Please see to it that the former Crown Prince is arrested
‫أرجوك احرصي على اعتقال وليّ العهد السابق
along with Lord Sangheon who escorted him here.
‫مع اللورد "سانغهيون" الذي رافقه إلى هنا.
You must demonstrate the weight of the royal family.
‫يجب أن تُظهري نفوذ العائلة المالكة.
He may be in exile,
‫قد يكون منفيًا،
but how can he be punished for attending his own father's funeral?
‫لكن كيف يُعاقب لحضور جنازة والده؟
Please let the Crown Prince pay his respects
‫أرجوك دع وليّ العهد يقدّم احترامه
to his father.
‫لأبيه.
Your Highness, there are rules that must be followed.
‫يا صاحبة السموّ، هناك قواعد يجب اتباعها.
If you cannot take action yourself,
‫إن كنت لا تستطيعين التصرف بنفسك،
I will order the soldiers instead.
‫فسآمر الجنود بدلًا من ذلك
To immediately arrest Lord Sangheon and the Crown Prince.
‫باعتقال اللورد "سانغهيون" ‫ووليّ العهد على الفور.
Great Lord Changcheon!
‫أيها اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون"!
I wish to speak with Her Highness alone,
‫أودّ التحدث إلى سموّها على انفراد،
so I would appreciate some privacy.
‫لذا أقدّر أن تمنحنا بعض الخصوصية.
Despite the circumstances, it was still wrong
‫رغم الظروف، كان من الخطأ
to bring His Royal Highness back.
‫أن تعيد صاحب السموّ الملكي.
The throne remains unoccupied,
‫ما يزال العرش شاغرًا،
so you must promptly decide who will succeed it, Your Highness.
‫لذا عليك أن تقرري بسرعة من سيخلفه سموّك.
Are you suggesting
‫هل تقترح
that I reinstate a Crown Prince who has been deposed?
‫أن أُعيد تنصيب وليّ العهد المخلوع؟
Would you rather hand the throne over to those who committed treason?
‫هل تفضّلين تسليم العرش للخونة؟
What are you saying?
‫ماذا تقول؟
Treason?
‫خيانة؟
Where is Prince Jehyeon?
‫أين الأمير "جيهيون"؟
Gyeom.
‫"غيوم".
Hwi.
‫"هوي".
Please forgive me.
‫سامحني أرجوك.
I failed to hold back my tears like you told me to do.
‫فشلت في حبس دموعي كما طلبت مني.
It is all right.
‫لا بأس.
It will all be fine.
‫سيكون كل شيء على ما يُرام.
It will be fine.
‫سيكون الأمر على ما يُرام.
Such insolence.
‫يا للوقاحة.
The deposed Crown Prince
‫وليّ العهد المخلوع
walks within the palace walls using the funeral as an excuse.
‫يمشي داخل أسوار القصر متذرعًا بالجنازة.
Is that why you wished to speak with me?
‫ألهذا السبب أردت التحدث معي؟
Lord Sangheon would not have brought back the Crown Prince
‫ما كان اللورد "سانغهيون" سيُعيد وليّ العهد
unless he had an ulterior motive.
‫لو لم يكن لديه دافع خفي.
Rumor is spreading across palace grounds that His Majesty was poisoned.
‫تنتشر في أرجاء القصر شائعة تقول ‫إن جلالته قد سُمم.
All I am saying is that
‫كل ما أقوله
we could play right into Lord Sangheon's hands.
‫هو إننا ربما نكون تصرفنا ‫كما يرغب اللورد "سانغهيون" من دون أن نعلم.
We?
‫نحن؟
I do not think I follow.
‫لا أظن أنني أفهم.
We joined forces and had the scholars make an appeal.
‫تعاونّا وجعلنا المثقفين يقدمون مناشدة.
Many are speculating that it drove a wedge between the King and me.
‫يتكهّن الكثيرون بأن ذلك ‫سبّب شرخًا بيني وبين الملك.
Before others try to use that as leverage--
‫قبل أن يحاول الآخرون ‫استخدام ذلك كوسيلة ضغط…
Some might get the wrong idea, Great Lord Changcheon.
‫قد يأخذ البعض فكرة خاطئة ‫أيها اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون".
You were the one who triggered the scholars' appeal.
‫أنت من حرّضت المثقفين على المناشدة.
All I did was inform you of what had happened
‫كل ما فعلته هو إبلاغك بما حدث
so that Lord Changun's voice could be heard.
‫حتى يصبح صوت اللورد "تشانغون" مسموعًا.
Are you choosing to back out now?
‫هل تختار التراجع الآن؟
As if I don't know what you truly desire.
‫كما لو أنني لا أعرف ما الذي ترغب فيه حقًا.
You thought you would be next in line with the Crown Prince out of the picture.
‫ظننت أنك ستكون الوريث التالي ‫بخروج وليّ العهد من الصورة.
The Crown Prince has Lord Sangheon in his corner,
‫يقف اللورد "سانغهيون" في صف وليّ العهد،
so Prince Jehyeon must have seemed like the easier target.
‫لذا لا بد أن الأمير "جيهيون" ‫بدا الهدف الأسهل.
Someone who is aware of that
‫من يدرك ذلك
should also know that actions have consequences.
‫يجب أن يعرف أيضًا أن للأفعال عواقب.
What did you just say?
‫ماذا قلت للتو؟
You must be well aware
‫لا بد أنك تعرف جيدًا
of the one who has the most to gain with the passing of His Majesty.
‫الشخص الذي سيحقق أكبر مكاسب من موت جلالته.
And what is clear to everyone
‫وما هو واضح للجميع
must be clear to Lord Sangheon as well.
‫لا بد وأنه واضح للّورد "سانغهيون" أيضًا.
10,000 BAGS OF RICE 100 HORSES
‫"عشرة آلاف كيس من الأرز، 100 حصان"
160 SHORT SWORDS 70 BOWSTRINGS
‫"مئة وستون سيفًا قصيرًا، 70 وتر قوس"
Great Lord Changcheon has amassed an army.
‫حشد اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون" جيشًا.
We both know what this implies.
‫كلانا نعرف ما يعنيه هذا.
He should be reprimanded for amassing an army,
‫يجب أن يُونّب لحشد جيش،
but it is not enough to accuse him of treason.
‫لكن هذا لا يكفي لاتهامه بالخيانة.
Recently…
‫مؤخرًا…
Great Lord Changcheon collided with the late King
‫اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون" ‫اصطدم بالملك الراحل
over his involvement regarding the scholars' appeal.
‫بشأن تورطه في مناشدة المثقفين.
His Majesty was well aware of Great Lord Changcheon's army.
‫كان جلالة الملك على دراية تامة ‫بجيش اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون".
Great Lord Changcheon must have feared the repercussions.
‫لا بد أن اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون" ‫كان يخشى التداعيات.
Could it be…
‫هل يمكن…
Are you saying…
‫هل تقول…
that Great Lord Changcheon had His Majesty poisoned?
‫إن اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون" ‫هو من دسّ السم لجلالته؟
The decision must be made.
‫يجب أن يتم اتخاذ القرار.
Will it be Prince Jehyeon whose forces committed treason or…
‫هل سيكون الأمير "جيهيون" ‫الذي ارتكبت قواته الخيانة أم…
the deposed Crown Prince?
‫وليّ العهد المخلوع؟
My Queen, Great Lord Changcheon shall enter.
‫يا ملكتي، ‫سيدخل اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون".
What happened?
‫ماذا حدث؟
I should have known better than to work with Lord Wonsan.
‫كان يجب أن أكون أذكى ‫وأمتنع عن العمل مع اللورد "وونسان".
How can he turn his back on me like this?
‫كيف يمكنه أن يتخلى عني هكذا؟
Rumor has it that you poisoned the King to prevent
‫تقول الشائعات إنك دسست السم للملك
being reprimanded for triggering the scholars.
‫كي تمنع تأنيبك بسبب تحريض المثقفين.
What can we do about this?
‫ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل حيال هذا؟
Damn it.
‫اللعنة.
You cannot go down like this.
‫لا يمكنك أن تسقط الآن.
Rally your troops, Father.
‫اجمع قوّاتك يا أبي.
-Pardon? -There is no time.
‫- عفوًا؟ ‫- ليس هناك وقت.
Write the letter. Do it now!
‫اكتب الرسالة، افعل ذلك الآن!
-You cannot do this. -Please!
‫- لا يمكنك فعل هذا. ‫- أرجوك!
-You cannot enter!
‫- لا يمكنكم الدخول!
Explain yourselves!
‫فسّروا تصرفكم!
They are traitors who murdered the King. Arrest them immediately!
‫إنهما خائنان وقتلا الملك، ‫اقبضوا عليهما حالًا!
-Yes, my lord. -What?
‫- حاضر يا سيدي. ‫- ماذا؟
What is the meaning of this?
‫ما معنى هذا؟
-How dare you. -Let go of me!
‫- كيف تجرؤون! ‫- اتركاني وشأني!
-How dare you grab me. -Let go of her!
‫- كيف تجرؤان على الإمساك بي! ‫- اتركاها وشأنها!
-How dare you lay a hand on the Queen? -How dare you!
‫- كيف تجرؤان على لمس الملكة! ‫- كيف تجرؤان!
Let go of me!
‫اتركاني وشأني!
Let go!
‫اتركاني!
How dare you lay your hands on me?
‫كيف تجرؤان على لمسي؟
My Queen!
‫ملكتي!
You had His Majesty's eunuch
‫جعلتما مخصيّ صاحب الجلالة
put poison in his herbal tonic.
‫يدسّ السم في المنشط العشبي خاصته.
What…
‫ماذا…
Before one plans a war,
‫قبل أن يخطط المرء لشن حرب،
one should choose his opponents wisely.
‫على المرء أن يختار خصومه بحكمة.
Lord Sangheon…
‫أيها اللورد "سانغهيون"…
-Take them away. -Yes, my lord.
‫- خذوهما بعيدًا. ‫- حاضر يا سيدي.
This is a set-up.
‫هذا فخ.
How dare you! I will have your head for this.
‫كيف تجرؤ! سأقطع رأسك ثمنًا لما فعلته.
-We are being framed! -Your Highness!
‫- قد تم الإيقاع بنا! ‫- سموّك!
Lord Sangheon!
‫أيها اللورد "سانغهيون"!
Your Highness!
‫سموّك!
I am curious as to why you came back though.
‫لكن يعتريني الفضول حيال سبب عودتك.
I only did so
‫لم أفعل ذلك
to bid farewell to our father.
‫إلا لوداع أبينا.
Hwi.
‫"هوي".
-Take him. -Yes, my lord.
‫- خذوه. ‫- حاضر يا سيدي.
What is this?
‫ما هذا؟
Hwi!
‫"هوي"!
Let go of me.
‫دعوني وشأني.
Let go!
‫اتركوني!
Prince Jehyeon was arrested.
‫اعتُقل الأمير "جيهيون".
What is this about?
‫ما الأمر؟
The Queen and Great Lord Changcheon
‫الملكة واللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون"
conspired to poison His Majesty.
‫تآمرا لتسميم جلالته.
But why?
‫لكن لماذا؟
Great Lord Changcheon had no reason to.
‫لم يكن لدى اللورد العظيم "تشانغتشيون" ‫سبب لفعل ذلك.
Reason is not a factor when it comes to one's desires.
‫لا يكون المنطق عاملًا ‫عندما يتعلق الأمر برغبات المرء.
The throne cannot be left vacant for too long,
‫يجب ألّا يبقى العرش شاغرًا لفترة طويلة،
so please collect yourself as soon as possible.
‫لذا أرجوك أن تستجمع قواك بأسرع وقت ممكن.
What are you saying?
‫ماذا تقول؟
-Am I-- -The one who stands before me…
‫- هل أنا… ‫- الشخص الذي يقف أمامي…
must sit on the throne.
‫يجب أن يجلس على العرش.
But I have already been deposed.
‫لكن تمّ خلعي مسبقًا.
The only eligible heir left is Prince Jehyeon.
‫الوريث الشرعي الوحيد المتبقي ‫هو الأمير "جيهيون".
Please release him this instant.
‫أطلق سراحه حالًا أرجوك.
I will return to where I belong.
‫سأعود إلى حيث أنتمي.
I am afraid you may not.
‫أخشى أنك لن تستطيع.
You fled with the help of your former tutor.
‫هربت بمساعدة معلّمك السابق.
Dying as a fugitive
‫الموت كهارب
who went on the run against His Majesty's orders
‫فرّ مخالفًا أوامر جلالته
is the only other option you have.
‫هو خيارك الآخر الوحيد.
Commander Yoon Hyeong-seol will have his limbs cut off.
‫سوف تُقطع أوصال القائد "هيونغ سيول يون".
Your eunuch and court lady will be beheaded.
‫سيتم قطع رأس مخصيّك وسيدة البلاط خاصتك.
And Jung Ji-un will be forced
‫وسيُجبر "جي أون جونغ"
to become a government slave.
‫على أن يصبح عبدًا للحكومة.
Do you wish to see
‫هل تريد أن ترى
how far I will go to make you the King?
‫إلى أي مدى سأصل لأجعلك الملك؟
Why…
‫لماذا…
Why must you go this far?
‫لماذا يجب أن تتمادى إلى هذه الدرجة؟
It's like I said.
‫كما قلت.
There is no reason behind the actions one takes to fulfill his desire.
‫لا يوجد سبب وراء الأفعال ‫التي يقوم بها المرء لتحقيق رغبته.
Take the throne.
‫اعتل العرش.
If you wish to protect your people,
‫إن كنت تريد أن تحمي شعبك،
you must have the power to do so.
‫فيجب أن تملك القوة لفعل ذلك.
Is no one out there?
‫ألا يوجد أحد في الخارج؟
Escort His Royal Highness to his quarters.
‫رافقوا صاحب السموّ الملكي إلى جناحه.
-Yes, my lord.
‫- حاضر يا سيدي.
Your Royal Highness!
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي!
Step aside. How dare you.
‫تنحّ جانبًا، كيف تجرؤ!
We were ordered by Lord Sangheon to escort him to his quarters.
‫أمرنا اللورد "سانغهيون" ‫بمرافقته إلى جناحه.
Any contact is forbidden.
‫يُمنع أي تواصل.
Are you all right, Your Royal Highness?
‫هل أنت بخير يا صاحب السموّ؟
Hyun.
‫"هيون".
I am glad to see you unharmed.
‫تسرّني رؤيتك سالمًا.
We will leave the palace.
‫سنغادر القصر.
Allow me to escort you.
‫اسمح لي بمرافقتك.
Lower your sword.
‫اخفض سيفك.
Was harming Commander Yoon and those who serve His Royal Highness not enough?
‫ألم يكن إيذاء القائد "يون" ‫وأولئك الذين يخدمون صاحب السموّ كافيًا؟
Must you treat him this way as well?
‫هل يجب أن تعامله بهذه الطريقة أيضًا؟
Do you not realize that you standing here unscathed
‫ألا تدرك أن وقوفك هنا سالمًا
is my last courtesy toward a royal relative?
‫هو آخر تصرف مُحترم أُظهره تجاه قريب ملكي؟
I heard that Lord Wonsan
‫سمعت أن اللورد "وونسان"
contributed greatly to the deposing of His Royal Highness.
‫ساهم بشكل كبير في خلع سموّه عن العرش.
This will be the last time that you
‫ستكون هذه آخر مرة بالنسبة لك
and your brother are given a pass due to your royal status.
‫ولأخيك للحصول على إعفاء ‫بسبب مكانتكما الملكية.
Do not forget that.
‫لا تنس ذلك.
Let go of me.
‫دعوني وشأني.
-Hyun! -Let go of me!
‫- "هيون"! ‫- دعوني وشأني!
Your Royal Highness.
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
Your Royal Highness!
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي!
SHINMUMUN
‫"شينمومون"
You fool.
‫أيها الأحمق.
Where is His Royal Highness?
‫أين صاحب السموّ الملكي؟
Do you have any idea what you have done?
‫هل لديك أدنى فكرة عمّا فعلته؟
I must meet the Crown Prince.
‫يجب أن أقابل وليّ العهد.
What did you hope to achieve by aiding his escape?
‫ما الذي أملت في تحقيقه ‫من خلال مساعدته على الهرب؟
Father!
‫أبي!
I must…
‫يجب…
meet His Royal Highness.
‫أن أقابل صاحب السموّ الملكي.
He is not someone you can meet at will now.
‫إنه ليس شخصًا يمكنك مقابلته متى شئت الآن.
What do you mean by that?
‫ماذا تعني بذلك؟
His coronation will soon take place,
‫سيتم تتويجه قريبًا،
so leave.
‫لذا ارحل.
Are you saying…
‫هل تقول…
he will become the King?
‫إنه سيصبح الملك؟
No.
‫لا.
No, that cannot be.
‫لا، هذا مستحيل.
Hwi.
‫"هوي".
Was…
‫هل كان…
Was it really my grandfather who poisoned our father?
‫هل كان جدّي حقًا من سمم والدنا؟
It's not true, is it?
‫هذا ليس صحيحًا، أليس كذلك؟
Please tell me it is not true.
‫أرجوك أخبرني أن ذلك ليس صحيحًا.
All my life I have been scared.
‫طوال حياتي كنت خائفًا.
I was scared that I might take your crown.
‫كنت خائفًا من أنني قد آخذ تاجك.
However…
‫لكن…
I was wrong all along.
‫كنت مخطئًا طوال الوقت.
I was scared that the greed and desire
‫كنت خائفًا من أن الجشع والرغبة
of my mother and grandfather
‫لدى أمي وجدّي
would land me here.
‫سيضعانني هنا.
Because that would lead to my death.
‫لأن ذلك سيؤدي إلى موتي.
The thought of it terrified me.
‫التفكير في الأمر أرعبني.
I am truly sorry, Gyeom.
‫أنا آسف حقًا يا "غيوم".
I…
‫أنا…
I thought the hardships only fell on me.
‫ظننت أن المصاعب كانت تنهمر عليّ فقط.
I thought it was only I who lived in fear.
‫ظننت أنني الوحيد الذي كنت أعيش في خوف.
It was I…
‫أنا…
who led our father to his death.
‫من تسبّبت في موت والدنا.
I am to blame for his passing.
‫أنا السبب في وفاته.
Do not worry.
‫لا تقلق.
I will save you.
‫سوف أنقذك.
You will not die.
‫لن تموت.
Never…
‫لن…
will I let them take your life.
‫أسمح لهم بقتلك أبدًا.
I will become King.
‫سأصبح الملك.
How you saved me from my demise…
‫وكيف أنقذتني من هلاكي…
and made me king…
‫وجعلتني ملكًا…
will never be forgotten.
‫لن يُنسى أبدًا.
However…
‫لكن…
I have a favor to ask.
‫أريد أن أطلب منك خدمة.
I am listening.
‫أنا أسمعك.
Please let Prince Jehyeon live.
‫أرجوك دع الأمير "جيهيون" يعيش.
Also, ensure the safety of my people.
‫احرص أيضًا على سلامة أتباعي.
Give me your word.
‫عدني بذلك.
If you do,
‫إن فعلت ذلك،
I will gladly become your puppet.
‫فسأصبح دميتك بكل سرور.
Will that be all?
‫هل هذا كل شيء؟
I am humbled by your boundless generosity,
‫أقدّر كرمك اللامحدود،
Your Majesty.
‫جلالتك.
Halt!
‫توقف!
Step aside.
‫تنحّوا جانبًا.
Are you all right?
‫هل أنت بخير؟
Your wound…
‫جرحك…
It must not be fully healed.
‫لا بد أنه لم يُشف تمامًا.
I am sorry.
‫أنا آسف.
I am…
‫أنا…
truly sorry.
‫آسف حقًا.
No.
‫لا.
Please tell me this is not true.
‫أرجوك أخبرني أن هذا ليس صحيحًا.
You promised me that we would be together.
‫وعدتني أننا سنكون معًا.
It is still not too late.
‫لم يفت الأوان بعد.
You can still leave the palace.
‫ما زال بإمكانك مغادرة القصر.
Allow me to escort you, so please--
‫اسمح لي بمرافقتك، لذا أرجوك…
As of this moment,
‫اعتبارًا من هذه اللحظة،
you are not allowed by my side.
‫ليس مسموحًا لك أن تكون بجانبي.
Forever.
‫إلى الأبد.
Then…
‫إذًا…
at least…
‫على الأقل…
allow me to tend to your wound.
‫اسمح لي بمداواة جرحك.
Bow.
‫انحنوا.
At ease.
‫استريحوا.
His Majesty shall now enter.
‫سيدخل جلالته الآن.
Let the morning assembly begin.
‫فليبدأ الاجتماع الصباحي.
I will stay by your side only until your wound has healed.
‫سأبقى إلى جانبك حتى يُشفى جرحك فحسب.
-The only desire I have is -Your Highness!
‫- رغبتي الوحيدة ‫- سموّك!
-to produce a son and make you happy.
‫- هي إنجاب ابن لأجعلك سعيدًا.
Please continue to let me handle these burdensome matters
‫أرجوك استمر في السماح لي بتولي ‫هذه المسائل المتعبة
so that you can give your full attention to producing an heir.
‫حتى يمكنك أن تولي اهتمامك الكامل ‫لإنجاب وريث.
I will keep that in mind.
‫سأتذكر هذا.
How is His Majesty? Has his wound healed?
‫كيف حال جلالته؟ هل التأم جرحه؟
His wound?
‫جرحه؟
Did you know all along?
‫هل كنت تعرف من البداية؟
Should anything happen to His Majesty, I will lose my mind.
‫إذا أصاب جلالته مكروه فسأفقد عقلي.
-I hope you will end it. -Hyun.
‫- آمل أن تنهي ذلك. ‫- "هيون".
His Majesty has become my whole world now.
‫أصبح جلالته عالمي بأكمله الآن.
Subtitle translation by: Hye-lim Park
‫ترجمة "مي جمال"